<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Contemplative pictures with wholesome precepts. The first part: Of God. Of the diuell. Of goodnesse. Of badnesse. Of heauen: and of hell. By Richard Bernard.</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849015</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09046)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 699:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Contemplative pictures with wholesome precepts. The first part: Of God. Of the diuell. Of goodnesse. Of badnesse. Of heauen: and of hell. By Richard Bernard.</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 134+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Hall for William Welbie, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Svvan,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Leaf A8 is a blank.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; all after page 34 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Emmanuel College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14143:1"/>
            <p>CONTEMPLATIVE PICTVRES: With WHOLESOME PRECEPTS. The firſt part:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Of God. Of the Diuell.</item>
               <item>Of Goodneſſe. Of Badneſſe.</item>
               <item>Of Heauen: <hi>and</hi> Of Hell.</item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD BERNARD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>William Hall</hi> for <hi>William Welbie,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard at the ſigne of the Swan. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14143:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14143:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable EDMVND Lord SHEFFEILD, Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter. Lord PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIDENT of his Maieſties Honourable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in the NORTH, and his Highneſſe Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant there. And to the right Honourable that his louingly obedient Lady VRSVLA the Lady SHEFFEILD.</head>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipfull La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, their Honourable iſſue, the Lady SVVIFT, and the Lady FAIR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FAXE: Heauenly ioies in Spirituall Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, good conſcience in obedience and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe glorie by faith in Chriſt: that grace and peace euermore.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE, RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ix diuided equallie to two, is three, or three to either. Three is all, ſo many to euerie one, no
<pb facs="tcp:14143:3"/> leſſe to any. A man is either of God by regeneration, liuing in goodneſſe, going to heauen; or of the diuell by corruption, practiſing wickedneſſe, and running headlong to hell. Two generations, the heauenlie race or the Serpents ſeed: two Regiments, ſome ſlaues by ſin to Satans controulement; ſome in voluntarie ſubiection by grace to Gods gouerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: two places to goe vnto, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall bottomleſſe pit, or the celeſtiall endleſſe paradiſe. There is but one Conductour, God in the ſpirituall bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but one ſeducer prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall,
<pb facs="tcp:14143:3"/> the diuell in ſpirituall darkeneſſe. One onelie true Religion, the reſt Idolatrie and Superſtition. There are no men Miſcellane, one betweene two of either, and yet neither. There is no meane or third place betwixt Hell below and Heauen one high. The Pope with his Prieſts may teach a Purgatorie, to picke the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of fooliſh Papiſts: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them thoſe that liſt, the word yeelds no ſuch war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, to cauſe a iudicious and ſound Proteſtant to feare or force of it. Yet is there one, an ill meane among men, that
<pb facs="tcp:14143:4"/> loathed creature, that Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warme Goſpeller: a time ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer profeſſing after his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as may ſtand with his profit: this is the Miſcellane man. But is hee good? then of God; then goe ſuch to heauen: but God ſaith hee will ſpue them (a tearme of loathing) out of his mouth: if bad, then of the Diuell, and ſo belong to Hell. Three and three then, <hi>God, Goodneſſe, Heauen: the Diuell, Badneſſe, Hell;</hi> my ſubiect matter empin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds all: none not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of theſe. God either guides men by his holie
<pb facs="tcp:14143:4"/> ſpirit, ſettles them in grace, and rewards them in heauen with infinite glorie: or the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell beareth ſwaie in their hearts and holds them in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, for which in hell they receiue wages due, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable miſerie.</p>
            <p>Heere therefore (<hi>RIGHT HONOVRABLE, RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</hi>) of all theſe are certaine pictures, not Popiſh and ſenſible for ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; but mentall for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine contemplation; whereto are added wholeſome Precepts for direction after godlie me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. Gods Picture, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb facs="tcp:14143:5"/> him, that is ſo good; to admire his excellencie, to feare his Maieſtie, to praiſe his bountie. The Diuels portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that he may be ſeene, that is ſo euill, to wonder at his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, to loath his vileneſſe, to deteſt his wretchedneſſe, and to beware of his deceitfulneſſe. Good is ſet forth, to behold the comelie beautie of celeſtiall grace, to embrace it with loue. Badneſſe is diſcouered, that the vglie morphew of ſinne may be ſeene, to abhorre it. Heauen is deſcribed to worke ioy in wel-doing by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo great a reward of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14143:5"/> and that eternally. Hell is deciphered to reſtraine from ſinne, by fearing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of vengeance in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall torments euerlaſtingly. He that doth good, may turne and read of God, his bleſſed guide; and of heauen, how in the end he ſhall bee in felicitie. He that doth euill, may read of the diuell, his accurſed leader; and of hell, and behold his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and dreadfull miſerie. This is the practicall vſe of theſe pictures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right Noble Lord;</hi> Still let the honouring of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and hatred of Poperie
<pb facs="tcp:14143:6"/> praiſe your zeale: this is of God. Let ſtill your ſpeedie execution of iuſtice make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned your ſeat of equitie: this is goodneſſe. Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours loue to the truth and regard of the miniſtrie is not vnknowne: your godly hate of Antichriſtianiſme is no leſſe manifeſt; and is not a care in iuſt proceeding betweene theſe two words, <hi>mine</hi> and <hi>thine,</hi> commended? Theſe giue ſure hope by Chriſt of heauen. My praier is for your Honours conſtant footing in this happie path. Indeede the way of wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing is ſtrait, and as narrow
<pb facs="tcp:14143:6"/> as ſtrait: hard to enter, and as difficult to endure therein: whereunto is required the wiſdome of a Serpent, and a Doues innocency. Godlie ſinceritie now adaies with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophels</hi> is held an affection from follie: iuſt and reſolute dealing, but a deſperate at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. The diſlike of Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmeneſſe, and hate of a falſe religion with <hi>Machiauellian Time-ſeruers</hi> is iudged but a paſſionate raſhneſſe, the heat of a ſpirit apt to Sedition.</p>
            <p>What if this be the wicked mans cenſure? What if the world, the Schoole of Satans
<pb facs="tcp:14143:7"/> policie, do thus condemne true Chriſtianitie? Muſt noble ſpirits ſet vp to aduance pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yeeld to ſuch helliſh Hags, and become ſlauiſh to the froth of vanitie? A true childe of the Church inſtructed in the Schoole of Chriſt, can not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it: his high ſpirit, eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted beyond the low pitch of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt reaſon in confederacie with fleſh and blood, poſſiblie cannot ſo debaſe it ſelfe. This were to ſeparate wiſdome and innocencie: to leaue religious ſinceritie, and to take vp other godleſſe mens impietie. Hee that can put in practiſe our
<pb facs="tcp:14143:7"/> Sauiours leſſon, to <hi>be as wiſe as a Serpent, and as harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe as a Doue,</hi> he may doe well. Together are they good; it is not ſeaſonable to be in act, while they bee aſunder. The firſt alone is but diuelliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe: the latter, by it ſelfe, is but a good meaning ſillineſſe: Hee that conioines them rightlie, ſeekes his owne ſafetie. Conſcience will plead for innocencie, God will defend it: and prudent practiſe keeps an eſtate good, maugre the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies malice. Where theſe two like to lodge and harbour in one heart, that, as rare, as
<pb facs="tcp:14143:8"/> excellent a perſon, may liue within himſelfe comfortably, among men peaceably, and in the end die ioyfully: my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined wiſh to your Honour and to all that walke with God vprightlie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right honourable Lady, Right Worſhipful and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable ofspring:</hi> My at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt may ſeeme a wonder; but the conceit of the wonderment ceaſeth where iudgement ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth out the cauſe, &amp; prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce doth guid wiſdom to weigh the circumſtance. A Lady is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored in her Lord, children are dignified in the due fame, and
<pb facs="tcp:14143:8"/> high promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their parents. The firſt are vnited by Gods ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the latter by natures influence. Whom God then and nature hath cemented, I, in my due honoring of al, preſume to conioine. Right Honourable Madame, and to you Ladies, I wiſh all welfare vnder God, on earth true goodnes, in heauen enduring gladnes; a time to read good things, but all times to practiſe, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your heartie aſſent this memorandum: Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are but weake, their ſtrength is to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der gouernment, excellent
<pb facs="tcp:14143:9"/> praiſe is gotten by their wiſe ſilence, but their principall glory ſtands in their awe, and cheerefull obedience. This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may not ſeeme a plauſible ſentence to your Sexe; but (good Ladies) he cannot flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that indeede doth giue you true Honour.</p>
            <p>I preſent your Honours, your Worſhips, with theſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall meditations, the firſt part of my <hi>Pictures and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</hi> Tho I bee troubled with controuerſies and called into ſuch matters of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet intermix I my ſtudie ſometime with theſe better mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb facs="tcp:14143:9"/> I finde that Queſtions curiouſly contriued doe more exerciſe wit, to informe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to make the heart deuout in our pilgrimage and this earthly exilement. By troubleſome diſputations men get knowledge to approue of good, but by quiet meditations men grow to more conſcience in their waies, and do increaſe in grace. Hence is my inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, and a cauſe of ſome ſtay of my anſwer both to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Ainſworth the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> and to <hi>Maſter Smith that Anabaptiſticall Se-Baptiſt:</hi> but now the time wil
<pb facs="tcp:14143:10"/> not be long, ere I publiſh my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie. This preſent labour, in the view of words, may ſeeme but litle, but the weight of the matter rightly valued makes it more. The heads here ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled are but few, yet comprehend much: the words not many; I haue ſtudied breuity: It is irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to be tedious, it is delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom to be ſhort and perſpicuous.</p>
            <p>It is (Right Honourable, Right VVorſhipfull) what it is, euen my good meaning, my firſt and beſt endeauour in this kind; whatſoeuer it bee, be it not, as it ſhould be, my will yet wiſheth it to bee well, and
<pb facs="tcp:14143:10"/> my thankfull heart offers it vp with all due reſpect vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou, and craues your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and worſhipful acceptances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the ſame. If I haue offended by tendering ſo ſmall a worke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſo great and worthy Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, I begge pardon for my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oldneſſe: and ſo praying for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our euer-proſperous eſtate and true happineſſe, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Worſop in Notinghamſ. <date>Nouem. 6.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours, and Worſhips to be commanded in the Lord, RICHARD BERNARD</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb facs="tcp:14143:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14143:11"/>
            <head>THE PICTVRE of GOD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD is by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction good, the prime cauſe of all his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuers: Onely one, one alone. Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, infinite, inuiſible. A ſubſtance without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, action without
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14143:12"/> motion. A being ſpiritual, of himſelfe eternall: before time, in time, and beyond altime: without beginning, without ending, the <hi>Alpha</hi> of euery thing, the <hi>Omega</hi> of althings: the <hi>firſt,</hi> &amp; the <hi>laſt:</hi> without terme of time. He is that kingly regencie, that lordly Souerainity. He doeth giue to all life, moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; he beſtoweth the qualitie and encreaſeth the quantitie: yet is he good without qualitie, and great without quantitie. Hee is the beeing &amp; beauty of his creature. Hee made euery
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14143:12"/> thing good, &amp; ſtil from him flowes goodneſſe; bodies bliſſe, ſoules ſafety, goods, preſeruation, and grace. He is Supereminent aboue all, Superexcellent beyond all, abundant in loue to all, and abſolutely in perfect happineſſe without all. He is the higheſt in maieſtie, the greateſt in glorie, the largeſt in magnificencie, the powerfulleſt in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie, and the euer one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſt in vnſpeakeable bounty. Without him no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing auaileable, with him all things poſſible, without,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14143:13"/> beſides, and againſt means. He is preſent euery where, without circumſcription of place, neither included heere, nor excluded there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee fils what is emptie, ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaineth what is weake, di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rects what is not right, go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerns what is inſtable, and perfects whatſoeuer is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> defect. Heauen is hiS throne the firmament hiS pauilion, Paradiſe his pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lace, the earth his theate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Angels are his attendants the Princes of his armie; al creatures his hoſt. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> azioured skie his comely
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14143:13"/> curtaine, his priuie cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the place of vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pleaſure. His face is a flame of fire, his voice thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, his wrath, dread, &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible horrour. If he meete his enemies, he rides vpon the wings of the winde, his chariots are without num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: he raineth vpon them ſnares to entrap them, fire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o deuoure them, haile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones to kill them; hee ſends a ſmoake to ſmother them, a ſtormy tempeſt to terrifie them, the ſtincke of brimſtone to annoy them, and hote thunderbolts to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14143:14"/> ſhoote them thorow. He is the Landlord to all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth; they are his Tenants, the beſt but his Stewards, the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt of his making. He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth by his power, ruleth by his prouidence; he hath in his hand a Scepter of iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and doth raigne as hee liſt, ouer him that ſeemeth to outrage the moſt. Satan is but his ſlaue, though hee rule ouer faithleſſe Princes and Peeres. The loftieſt creature, the higheſt man in Souereigntie, is but his footſtoole, and hardly a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14143:14"/> ſhadow of his gliſtering glory, &amp; glorious emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. Hee foreſeeth euery thing before it be, wiſely orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth al things that are, and preordeineth all certainely what ſhall be. There is no preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of his wil, no gain ſaying of his good pleſure: his power manageth his wil vnreſiſtably; his wil is the rule of righteouſneſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geably: he maketh euery thing to bow at his becke: he altereth the order of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; changeth the courſe of times. He can ſpan hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with his hand, ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14143:15"/> depth of the Ocean feas, make the earth tremble at his preſcence. Something he can make of nothing, &amp; the leaſt ſomething is hee able to multiply into in. numerable many things. He is admirable in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, and wonderfull in the creation: By ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his infinitneſſe, hee left an inanity of ſubſtance, forme, and force; ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared he vnſpeakeably an emptines to frame &amp; place his creatures: by reduction of himſelf againe innarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he made a kind of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14143:15"/> and cauſed that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to be ſeene, what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer had being of any thing before. All his works liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrate him; his word truely reueales him: yet no mortall eye can ſee him, nor any wit conceiue him. Hee is mercy, hee is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, a fire burning, and yet not haſtily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuming. He is al preſence, his nameis, <hi>I am,</hi> nothing paſt with him, nor to come which is not in ſight. Infiniteneſſe it ſelfe is his compaſſe, for time and place. His iuſtice is without parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14143:16"/> he iudgeth euer righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, and puniſheth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offenders, and that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedly. His pleaſure is abſolute in himſelfe; what he delighteth in, without himſelfe, is for that, which is onely from himſelfe. To conclude an endleſſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter without concluſion; He is merciſull without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, pitifull in great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, but without any paſſion. Hee is repentant without ſorrow, he maketh a change in his action, but is neuer alterable in his perſon. Hee is himſelfe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14143:16"/> the very fountaine of all goodneſſe,: nothing euill from him, nothing euil by him. He before wils all things, which he cauſeth to be, and maketh alſo that good which hee willeth to bee. Hee is maieſtie, hee is mercy, he is excellency, he is glory, he is power, he is principality, hee is grace and goodnes, life and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. All theſe, in, and from himſelfe, in all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, beyond imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without limitation, endleſſe. To him be praiſe perpetually. So be it.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14143:17"/>
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>FEare this God, beleeue him to bee, know him rightly, behold him inuiſibly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him without Idolatry. Remember euer his preſence, conſider his powerfull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Thou art of him, thou art in him, thou waſt made for him. Seeke his friendſhip, force of nothing in reſpect of his fauour. Loue him aboue all, hold on his ſide againſt all, and be ſubiect to him before all: reuerence thou his maieſtie, obey his commands awe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, in all actions ſeeke his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14143:17"/> glorie, and praiſe his name con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, that thou maieſt of him be bleſſed eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14143:18"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14143:18"/>
            <head>The Picture of the holy Trinity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD, the true God, is but one in vnity, yet three in Trinity: One in ſubſtance without diuiſion, three in perſon by diſtinction, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt. In order, one afore and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an other: but eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all coequall, coeternall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14143:19"/> together. Al God, not three Gods, yet euer three per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, neuer the ſame in pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priety &amp; maner of working Heere is admiration, but no demonſtration. This Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholik and Chriſtian verity is an innarrable myſtery.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>BEleeue this, the word tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth it; but corrupt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is againſt it. Beware of cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious ſearching, it is a matter vnſearchable. Stand not vpon this to know how it may bee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſubiect thy reaſon to faith in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14143:19"/> ſobriety. It is a godly ignorance, in that to be vnskilfull, which the Scripture concealeth. Hee that ſuffers herein his reaſon to wade farther than faith, may loſe his reaſon and beliefe, his Chriſtianitie for infidelity. Preſume not (ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aboue that which is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is a deep myſtery, this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Deity, the inſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table point in Diuinity. The Lord giue thee true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, reſolued faith, with reuerend feare.</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14143:20"/>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14143:20"/>
            <head>The Picture of the Father.</head>
            <p>IN the vnity, the Father is the firſt in the Trinity. He is not begotten, but from euerlaſting begetteth the Son, of his whole ſubſtance. He made all things by the Sonne, through the holie Ghoſt. What he willed hee made good, and all of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by his word. This gracious father of his mere
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14143:21"/> mercie, hath choſen many, without their merite. He calles his ere they come; &amp; when they come, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes their faith. He knows them before they bee, and makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> friends by grace of deadly foes by nature; of Sathans ſlaues, his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Seruants; of Seruants, deare Sonnes, children a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted, yea kings, prieſts and Coheires with Chriſt. He careth for his children, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he moſtcaſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down: He can allow them their godly will, but he permits them not to be wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14143:21"/> they do offend, hee will fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly forewarn; if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, he will not puniſh. He is full of commiſeration, he doth ſpeedily pardon the Penitent, and withall ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth great gladneſſe to doe them good. He doth ſend them his ſpirit, to aſſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of peace, &amp; freely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to beſtow on them grace, either to preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their fal, or to pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fault. Though we be neither wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of beeing, nor breath, and deſerue nothing, yet he affoords vs his <hi>bleſſing,</hi> and giueth needfully anything.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14143:22"/> Earthly Fathers are ſuch, as they be, for a ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but this Heauenly Father is ſo for euerlaſting. He forbeareth with patience, and keepes his in eternal remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. He hateth neuer, where hee loueth euer. Bountifull hee is in his bleſſings, largious in his liberality, full graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fauourable, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end in goodneſſe. Hee is ſtrict, but not extreame in iuſtice: Hee calleth man to make ſatisfaction vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on paine of deſtruction: yet if man can make no pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his mercy hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14143:22"/> meanes to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the debt. Ere ſinfull man do die, his ſinleſſe Son muſt ſuffer death. Wrath muſt not reward vs, his great goodneſſe will needs haue vs guiltleſſe. Is not his loue enlarged towards vs vnſpeakably? doth he not purchaſe vs peace with the price of bloud? He gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth an obedient Sonne, for a rebellious Sinner: Wrath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpleaſure muſt ſeaſe vpon Gods naturall Sonne and an innocent, that pity may be ſhewed to adopted childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to eſcape torment.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14143:23"/> The euer worthily beloued muſt vndergoe paines of Hel, to make for the vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of loue, free paſſage to Heauen. See (Sinner) ſee the incredibleneſſe of ſo great grace: Stand (thou Sinner) amazed, at this wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of good. O match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe mercy! Did euer a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfie his wrath vpon his deareſt ſon, to appeaſe his anger towards his dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foe? did euer a louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put his darling to death, to preuent from his enimy the force of his wrath? We ſee it not, ſtories
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14143:23"/> record it not, nature ſuffers it not. Yet this father killeth his beſt Sonne, to kiſſe his worſt creature; forſaketh the Gracious, for a time, to receiue the Graceleſſe to mercy, for euer.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>OH therefore let vs euer loue and praiſe the Lord this heauenlie Father for his goodnes: Oh let vs not ceaſe to declare the wonders which he doth for vs the children of men!</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14143:24"/>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:14143:24"/>
            <head>The Picture of the Sonne.</head>
            <p>THe Son is the ſecond perſon in the Trinity, the Fathers naturall Son begotten fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternity, the Image and ſubſtance of his Father without ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality. From the father, by the Holy Ghoſt, hee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth together with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all things: he is God, he is man, perfect in both natures. He hath a Father,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14143:25"/> he hath a mother, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both truely; &amp; alſo no father, nor mother but reſpectiuely. He is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-God, &amp; God-ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; yet not two perſons, but onely one Chriſt: One not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, but by aſſumption; not by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but by vnity of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This is the ſeed promiſed; the prophet foretold the prince of peace. This is <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech,</hi> the prieſt of the high God, the king of <hi>Salem,</hi> the Iewes Meſſiah, the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Sauiour. This is he that wil ſummo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all to appear, &amp; giue true iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14143:25"/> both quik &amp; dead in the laſt day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here he va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed ſubdued the fleſh &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the world. He hath mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated Gods wrath, perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med our work: iuſtice is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied, the law fulfilled. Hee hath made an attonement, obtained mercy, &amp; freed vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puniſhment. The father of his mercy gaue him for vs, &amp; hee in loue beſtowed himſelf of vs. The father did wil our peace, &amp; hee ſpared no paines. Hee came into the world poore, to make vs ritch. Hee was to the wicked a deriſion, that wee with Angels might bee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14143:26"/> had in admiration. He was blaſphemed, to make vs bleſſed; buffeted and ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to make vs ſecure in true comfort. He wrought righteouſneſſe, that wee might bee free of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Hee was innocent, to procure vs pard on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing penitent. His holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is our happineſſe, his ſuffering our ſafety, his grace our good. Hee was heere in trouble for vs, his life paineful and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo his end for vs dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and his torments intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable. In all his life, that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14143:26"/> wee read of, hee did neuer laugh; but often lament: Hee mourned to ſee mens madneſſe, and wept for their wo. Here he ſighed ſore to make vs ſing, hee ſobd and ſorrowed much to make vs merrie. Hee bare vpon him vnutterable torment pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, that wee might auoid the plagues of God eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. His prayers were loud cries and ſtrong, to make our praiers to pierce the Heauens. He ſweat drops of bloud to purge and ſweeten vs vnto our God: hee cried with bitter tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14143:27"/> vpon the croſſe, to ſaue his ſeruants from the dreadfull curſe. He did die as a malefactor, to become to euery beleeuer a beneſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour. Euil did he none, wee are the offenders; Heauen is his deſert, Hell ours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: wee haue merited damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and he purchaſt for vs ſaluation. Wee were bound to the Law, we were vnder the curſe, in danger of death, and ſubiect to wrath: but hee hath ſent vs his Goſpel, preched peace, promiſed pardon, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained grace. If the law
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14143:27"/> would condemne vs, hee hath fulfilled it for vs; his works preuent wrath, his croſſe, the curſe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience by the law would accuſe, the Goſpell by grace will quiet it and acquite vs. If iuſtice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand her due, his paines were our full paiment. Hee is the waie for vs to walke in. Hee is the trueth, wee may beleeue him. Hee is the life, happy is he that liues in him. By him and through him all our wants are ſuplied, and all grace and goodnes obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14143:28"/> Are we in corruption? His purity purgeth vs. Are we diſobedient? Hee was moſt obedient. Are we ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to wrath? he couers vs. Wander we? he recouers vs. Seeke we ſafety? He af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foords vs ſolace. Want we a ſurety? He is our pledge. None in ſo great debt, but he can diſcharge: None ſo in diſgrace, but he can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him peace. He is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended for life, that wee might not deſcend to the place of death. Wee need not feare the Law, Sathan, ſinne: hee hath gotten vs
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14143:28"/> heauen, life and ſaluation, without daunger of Hell, death or damnation.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>HEre is peace (O happy man) &amp; by Chriſt procured. Seek in him thy ſoules ſafety: Behold heer ioy &amp; ſpiritual ſecurity. Call boldly God father, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this Ieſus to be thy brother. Belieue in him, &amp; conſtantlie rely on him. Loue him, and long for him; ſay, when Lord? how long Lord? come Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, come quickly. In the meane ſpace, liue in loue, worke righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſeeke peace in holines, keepe in the limits of ſobriety,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:14143:29"/> continue in chaſtitie, and bee neuer without charitie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect aſſured felicity: which the father of mercy euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more grant thee,</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14143:29"/>
            <head>The Picture of the Holy Ghoſt.</head>
            <p>HE is the third perſon, his property is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from the Son. He works euer from both, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with both. Hee is Chriſts Vicegerent in his kingdome,<note place="margin">The Pope may bee packing as the diuels darling.</note> his onely Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car General in his Church. Hee raiſed vp the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, hee inſtructed the Apoſtles, and now qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14143:30"/> all Chriſts true meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. The bad he maketh good, in the good hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth grace. He reforms our waies, informes our iudgement, and confirmes our faith. Hee changeth diſcord into duties of loue, and turneth all miſdeeds, into Almes deedes; prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into deuoute praier, fooliſh prating into power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and perſwaſiue prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: the Preachers tong he makes the pen of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy writer. Euill luſts, wher hee commeth, hee killeth, the dead works of darkenes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14143:30"/> he expelleth. He is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſanctifying the elect; hee is not partiall, but dealeth meaſurably to all, without ſiniſter reſpect. He is to the Saints the bleſſed Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; hee perſwades them all, to call God Father. He works repentance, and giueth therupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true peace of conſcience. Chriſts Church is his Temple, and he the ſaueguard of his ſheep. He ſignifieth our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narrable ſighs, and maks vs expreſſe our deſires in prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er vnto God. He helps vs to indite, to frame our wils,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14143:31"/> to make our meditations, to moderate our affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; orderly to diſpoſe al our actions. Our eics by him do ſee into the Scriptures, he is the true commentarie to vnderſtand the word. Hee learneth men to handle controuerſies, without con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion; &amp; to make a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but without Schiſme. By him croſſes are not without comfort, and the day of proſperitie, not without meditation of a change. He maketh euery thing to the godly profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the greateſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14143:31"/> neuer inſupportable. It is onely he that worketh in his faith by the word, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtful weariſomnes of the world, a hopefull perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of heauen, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dreadfull feare of hell. Hee knits piety to right policy, and ſeuereth true deuotion, from fooliſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. Here in this life hee beginneth grace, ſets on to goodneſſe, perſwads to holineſſe, vrgeth to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſſe, preſſeth on to godlie practiſe, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tling the ſoule in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious pureneſſe, and ſo
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14143:32"/> leades it forward with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued conſtancie to end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe happineſſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects all in the life to come.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>OH (vnſtable man) get the ſtrength by this Spirit, pray him earneſtlie to ſettle thy ſoule in ſafetie. Make him thy maſter; his motions, thy firſt mouer. Aduiſe by his Counſell, walke euer by his courſe. Silence thy ſelfe, when he giues ſentence; bee not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, if he doe cenſure. Beſtow thy ſelfe by his direction, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14143:32"/> willingly be led, by his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. If he premoniſh, be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned; if hee call backe, run not on. Stay, Where hee bids thee ſhop, and ſtand not when he moueth thee to ſet forward. If thou haſt him not, intreat the Lord to ſend him: If thou haſt him, carefully hold him. If thou wouldeſt trie the true Spirit, diſcerne his motions by the word; his habitation in thee by ſanctified worke. The Scripture is his Scantling, hee works not ordinarilie, but as the word doth warrant, and hee abids in none that are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and diſobedient. Bee no
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14143:33"/> Schiſmaticke; he will forſake thee; be no Heretique, be will not harbour with thee. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe not him, deſpight him not by thy prophanenes: If thou quench his grace thou looſeſt thine owne good. Let him guide thee after the word, and thou ſhalt bee euer well-pleaſing to God, accompanied of Angels, approued of godlie men, and be rewarded in heauen: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit the bleſſed trinitie vouchſaf thee (Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14143:33"/>
            <head>The Picture of the Diuell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee is that dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Ghoſt, the firſt ſiner, the firſt Seducer: One knowing much, yet neuer obedient, but by conſtraint. Hee is but a Slaue, as baſe, as he is beggerly: as mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, as curſedly miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous. Blaſphemouſly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of God, tyrannouſly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14143:34"/> cruell to men. A continual Tempter, Gods gaoler, a dreadfull tormentor. Euer is he out with God, and a hater of the good. What God commands, hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes; hee will allow, what God diſlikes. A bright Angell, hee was in heauen; but now the black Fiend in hell. To no man a frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to the Church a moſt malicious foe. He is driuen out of the penitent, he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in the diſobedient<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The leaud are his lodging the prophane his habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Hee is the vncleane
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14143:34"/> ſpirit, the place moſt full of abomination, is his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon harbour. All his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, are to ſatisfie luſt, he would haue vs liue after our liking, to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, to rage in rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt God. He knows himſelfe to be damned; all he cares for, is to make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like himſelfe. This curſed ſpirit, is that <hi>Lion</hi> roaring, ſtrong, fearefull: that <hi>old Serpent,</hi> ſubtil, guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: that <hi>red Dragon,</hi> bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, terrible. Hee raigneth where hee gets any rule, and whom hee gaineth,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14143:35"/> thoſe willingly hee will not let goe. Antichriſt is his eldeſt ſonne, the damned crue his curſed children. He is the inuent our of all villanie, the authour of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, the ſetter vp of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, the plotter of conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie. He raiſeth rebellion, and workes treaſon. Hee turnes religion into ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, loue into lecherie, friends into foes, conſent into contention, peace into bloody perſecution. Hee comes where the godly bee and good excerciſes, not for loue to them, but mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14143:35"/> as an inſtrument to hinder them. He will ſend <hi>Caine</hi> to ſacrifice with <hi>Abel,</hi> but afterwards to murther him: He will thruſt <hi>Iudas</hi> among the Apoſtles, but to betray Chriſt. He is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie enuious, as malicious: If Chriſt plant a Church, he will erect a Chapell; if hee haue Apoſtles, this will raiſe vp falſe teachers; If Chriſt ſow wheat, hee will ſcatter tares. He deceiued <hi>Eue,</hi> which brought a curſe to the earth: Hee prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Dauid,</hi> to fall to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that the people
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14143:36"/> might be plagued. Hee is that grand Lier, that ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Slanderer: He is as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, as irrepentant. He tempted Chriſt himſelfe impotunately, hee vexeth his members, and that dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. He is ful of faire words, hee makes many promiſes, but doth neuer performe what is good. He is a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiauellian, when hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth moſt to doe well, then hee intendeth moſt miſchiefe, and to doe ill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hee keepes men in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and perſwades them of faith; hee puts them in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14143:36"/> hope of ſaluation, and yet diſſwades from the grace of ſanctification. Hee would haue the wickedly diſpoſed to preſume of mercy, and the godly peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to deſpaire in appre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>henſion of iuſtice. Hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth his to beleeue, that good meaning without the word, is warrant enough in Gods worſhip, and blind deuotion, to bee a great growth in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends wickedneſſe with ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of goodneſſe: He puts a faire vizour ouer the vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie face of ſinne. Exceſſiue
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14143:37"/> pride muſt be cleanely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; no pompe. Filthy luſt, but a tricke of youth; no carnality. Bad compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, with pot-mates, good fellowſhip; no vanitie. Couetouſneſſe in the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, thrifty husbandrie; no ſordid qualitie. Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall expences frankhear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes; no vnthriftineſſe. Inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peratenes in meetings, neighbourly meriments; no gluttonie, nor drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Riot, recreation; idle muſing, contemplation. Thus hee blindeth him that cares not to ſee ſinne,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14143:37"/> that ſo a man may bee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, in haſtning to hell. Hee that is moſt in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, is his beſtſonne; yet is the greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, his baſeſt Slaue. Who ſo doth moſt for him, ſhall in the end, bee moſt tormented by him. God commands his children for their owne ſaluation; but Satan his ſeruants, to bring them to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All his are either car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Atheiſtes, groſſe Idolaters, Hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Time-ſeruers; foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14143:38"/> ſuperſtitious, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably miſchieuous, proud Heretikes, or idle headed Schiſmatiks. Hee will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſome of his to bee of the viſible Church, yet onely a <hi>Came,</hi> an <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophel,</hi> a <hi>Saul,</hi> a <hi>Iudas,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inuiſible grace. Hee wil giue them leaue to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, but not to practiſe. He lets them know verity, but not acknowledge it with ſincerity; their ſeruice is only faſhion. Hypocrits are his Saints, cuſtome his Canon, Sophiſtrie his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. His kingdome is dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14143:38"/> Schiſmatikes, his zealous ſeruants; Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, his chiefe Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. His company the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, the prophane his principall attendants, next to the Fiends, the helliſh inhabitants. The reward to his, wrath from God; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the good. The place for their abode, is the infernall pit, there to bee tortured in torment, and plagued with erernall paines without end.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14143:39"/>
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>OH wretched ſinner, ſeeke peace to thy poore ſoule: ſeale not vp thy damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by doing ſeruice to this Diuell. Stop thy eares, heare him not: if thou doeſt, beleeue him not. Wherein he moſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a Saint, therein hold him a moſt accurſed creature. Tho his promiſes pretend peace and ſaluation, yet euer in his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, denie his concluſion. Make no peraduenture of the word; if thou doeſt, hee will forthwith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradict the truth.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14143:39"/> If thou be a doubting <hi>Eue,</hi> to ſay, <hi>leſt I die,</hi> hee will bee a <hi>Serpent,</hi> and dare confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſay, <hi>thou ſhalt not die.</hi> Be not: a ſlaue to him, that made ſuite to lodge in Swine. Bee not ruled by him, if thou beeſt trulie penitent, who reigneth onely ouer the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. Bee no ſubiect to ſo baſe an abiect: nor a friend to ſo great a foe. Leaue his luſts, elſe looke for no life. Forſake the world, elſe thou gaineſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the word. If thou wilt needs be led by him, looke for no Heauen: if thou ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſinne, prepare for Hell. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14143:40"/> the end, the due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of wickedneſſe, both in the diuell, and the damned. From which miſerie, the God of compaſſion deliuer thee (Reader) of his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercie.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:14143:40"/>
            <head>The Picture of Goodneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Oodnes is grace, a picture of God: the worſt in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall approue it, but the Saints ſpecially reioice in it. It is heauens path-way, the righteous mans ayme: no earthly thing can pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe it, it is onely God that giues it. In it ſelfe it is beyond any price, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14143:41"/> other things preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. It is the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween creature &amp; creature, between men &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their words and works. Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe makes man good, the perſon, his ſpeech and practiſe. It baniſheth bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe, forceth fraud to be flying, allayeth conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious heate of ſpirit, and meekneth the vntameable nature of man. It ſuffereth no reuengement, it is not rigorous in puniſhment. Loue ſprings from it, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience waits of it, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie vſhers it. It is that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14143:41"/> which makes a man friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, to procure reliefe for the needy; and without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay to helpe the diſtreſſed ſoule. It is defectiue of no dutie, it is pliable to al the works of mercy. Will is neuer wanting by good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, tho ability be away. It inhabiteth euer in true piety, and lodgeth with godly pitie. It baniſheth malice and michiefe farre from it, and is a deadly bane to rancour and rage. It forbeareth a fiecre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary very quietly; wher it may fully reuenge, it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14143:42"/> readily. It will paſſe by wrong through mercy, yet not ſhew partial pitie, to ouerthrow iuſtice; it keeps moderation and meaſure in all things. It is borne vp of humility, ſtrengthned by patience; the word of life doth nouriſh it, the Lord of life doth cheriſh it; the ſpirit giues it quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Gods glory ſets it on working. It is from heauen aboue, in earth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained of few: he is full that hath it, and he euer in want that is without it. It moues vs to minde God
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:14143:42"/> more then goods, the Lords precepts, more then our profits. It thinkes of death before death, to be fit for death. It prepares the body for the earthly graue, and the ſoule for the heauenly glory It brings to a man peace within, and praiſe abroad; heere commendation, and after ſaluation. This is goodneſſe, the forme is true godlineſſe, the cauſe is grace. It maks a man ſtudy to be quiet, it keeps pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence within vs, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about vs, wickednes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14143:43"/> farre from vs. Good is hee, that hath this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he ſhall attaine to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting happineſſe.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>LAbour to come to this goodneſſe, dwell with it: harbour vnder it. Let it grace thy perſon, and commend thy condition. Let thy words declare it, and thy workes paint it out to the world. Thou ſhalt by goodneſſe get with God fauour, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong good men friendſhip:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14143:43"/> which the God of goodneſſe giue vnto thee now and alwaies:</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:14143:44"/>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14143:44"/>
            <head>The Picture of Badneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His is ſinne, the cretures defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the will from God, and the minde from good. It is the ſeed of Satan, the fruit of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and mans deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. The Diuel is the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> concupiſcence the <hi>Mother.</hi> The Serpent ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14143:45"/> ſuggeſted it, our firſt parents fooliſhly did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine it. Satan yet is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in begetting it, worldly obiects prouoke it, the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes let it in vnto the ſoule. Conſent is <hi>conception,</hi> the heart is the <hi>wombe</hi> of conceiuing. It <hi>quickneth</hi> by fleſhly reaſons, it <hi>trauelleth</hi> in deſire to bee doing. It bringeth foorth by oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, the <hi>Midwife;</hi> expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling firſt Gods feare, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide his precepts, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning his preſence. Holy piety hath heere no place, conſcience is not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14143:45"/> called to this buſineſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies is quite out of minde, thoughts of his wrath hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the earth: Gods word muſt be no warrant, goodneſſe is forgotten. Theſe bring not ſinne to birth, theſe hinder ſin for comming forth. Doubting of Gods word makes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, luſt laies it in bed, infidelity brings it to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. It is wrapt in vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, it is laid in the <hi>cradle</hi> of ſecurity. The Diuel cloſeth the eies with ignorance, and filleth the eares with
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14143:46"/> Sophiſtrie: the head is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with preſumption of mercy, ouer the heart is laid hardneſſe, the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ouerſpread with blindneſſe. It is <hi>nurſed</hi> by the world, <hi>ſuckled</hi> vpon the breaſts of pleaſure and profit. It growes great by cuſtome, and ſpreads by community. Bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples doe countenance it, plauſible tearms confirme it. It is <hi>cloathed</hi> with the hope of pardon, tied with the <hi>girdle</hi> of common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors, imagined to bee of Gods ſpecial grace Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14143:46"/> attends it, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of time enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, giues it reſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of finding fauour in the end, <hi>rocks</hi> it aſleepe. Sinnes <hi>ſleepe</hi> is conſcience deadneſſe, the iudgements blindneſſe, the wils per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeneſſe, affections diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderlineſſe, and a reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued careleſneſſe. Tho ſinne haue ſuch a ſleepe, yet ſometime vpon a fearefull terror, it will ſuddenly <hi>awake:</hi> and waking, the pleaſant ditty of Satans <hi>ſong</hi> gets it ſoone aſleepe againe. It hath foure parts:
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14143:47"/> the <hi>Tenor,</hi> carke and care thou for the world: the <hi>Meane,</hi> thou maieſt repent when thou wilt: the <hi>Treble,</hi> reioice thy ſelfe in thy youth: the <hi>Baſe,</hi> thinke death is not yet at hand. Heereby it ſnorts in a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſafety, ſpreads in bredth, waxeth big, and hie by hardneſſe of heart. It is very foule at the firſt, worſe by continuance, but loathſome at the laſt. It baſtard-like, brings ſhame to the begetters, diſgrace to the abettours, confuſion to the followers. Where it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:14143:47"/> getteth ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, there hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie it is caſt out: where it is not timely maſtred, there it wil haue the vpper hand. It is lordly, and couets to rule: it is raging, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous, if it raigne. Hee that ſubdues it, eaſily kils it; and hee that ſtriues not to ſtifle ſinne, workes his owne woe, and neglects his owne ſafetie. Sin where it is not killed, will kill; if it die, we liue; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it liue, we die moſt certainely. It was at the firſt, perſonall; it is now original, and naturall: From Gods mercie in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14143:48"/> onely veniall; in it ſelfe and in all other, deadlie and mortall. Good is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pleaſure is conceiued in the conſent, and ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is approued, by the heart deceiued, till the time come of torment. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſoules bewitched with the works of the fleſh, know not the euill of ſinne: but behold and ſee, how it defaceth Gods image, makes man a monſter; of Gods child, the diuels creature. It diſlodgeth goodneſſe, it keepes out
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14143:48"/> godlines; inwardlie it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights the hart with filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and outwardlie ſets the hand to act vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. God and man by it are at ods, who werebefore at one: the Earth in creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bleſſed, by tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is accurſed. It takes from vs what good we haue, &amp; brings the euils vppon vs, which naturallie we hate. It caſt the Angels out of Heauen, Adam out of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe; by it <hi>Reuben</hi> loſt his birthright, Iudas his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip, by it commeth death to men terribile, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14143:49"/> their perſons to God exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable. It maketh the Law condemne vs, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to accuſe vs. By it godlie exerciſes grow loathſome, godly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie becomes irkeſome. No bleſſing ſhould bee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, if ſinne put not in a barre: euer contentment, without diſcomfort: euer internall peace, without externall diſgrace. It is wickedneſſe, that workes our wretchedneſſe. Shame is ſinnes raiment, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the cognizance, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the praiſe, an ill
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14143:49"/> name the recompence. In itſelfe it is vanity, the gaine but miſery. It is a ſtrife with the truth, an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie againſt veritie, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie againſt ſincerity. It is a conflict with God, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of goodneſſe: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worſe then heerein to haue the victory. Mans oppoſing of the word, is a taking part with Satan, againſt the Lord: and mans ioy in ſinning, is to be glad of the diuels trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing. All men haue ſinne, but hee that committeth ſinne, is a ſlaue to ſinne.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14143:50"/> It rules in ſome, in other it is ruled: Hee that makes the leaſt of it, ſhall, as with wiſards, haue leaſt to doe with it. It is as an impudent gueſt; tho it come ſeldome, yet is euer troubleſom; ſmal kindneſſe doth work great boldneſſe; much curteſie, intollerable ſaucineſſe. It is euer to the godly vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſpirit; if but once in act, yet greatly grieuous; if it be liked, and often wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and neuer forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, there grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will grow into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and the partie
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14143:50"/> runne headlong into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. It is of diuers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and keepes not one ſhape; it is of diuers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and not of one ſort In one it is pride &amp; lordly, in an other humility in ſhew, but indeed hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. In the cholerike it is ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, in ſome other nature luſtfull. It is ſomtime adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, and maks a man fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; it is ſometime dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and makes a man beaſtly. It hath the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, ten witneſſes to name it; it hath alſo the ſame law to declare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:14143:51"/> it. One precept tearmes it Idolatrie, an other ſaith it is adultery: this maketh it ſuperſtition, that trecherie and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as the Law looks vpon ſinne, ſo the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doe name it, and thereupon withall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime it. It turnes a man into it ſelfe, and makes a man to ſhew it, againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. One ſinne is linked in with another, and euery one forceth out the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fruit, of it owne nature. By couetouſneſſe man growes niggardly, an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:14143:51"/> vnmercifull: by pride, arrogant, hauty and hatefull: by gorman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing, gluttonous; by faithleſneſſe, treacherous: by ignorance, ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; by carnall ſeruice, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous: by contempt of other, and abuſe of wit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the word, hereticall; and by immoderat paſſion, and ſtrong affection, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall. It is in euery one more or leſſe; the childe hath it, but knowes it not: the yong man is caried with it, but cares not; the grown man forced with it,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:14143:52"/> but reſiſts not: and old age with it Crammocklike crooked, but feeles it not. Yet is nothing more in vſe to be knowne; more hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering mans good, to be auoided; more ſubtill, to be looked vnto; more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, to be felt; more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, to bee preuented; more forcibly aſſaulting vs, to be ſtrongly of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. By it Satan gets of the heart poſſeſſion; by it is hindered the ſpirits illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by ſinne is darkned, our thoughts from God
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:14143:52"/> eſtranged; the heart in goodneſſe is fainted, the faculty of the will weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the quietneſſe of conſcience interrupted. Faith fals to doubting, hope lets goe her hold, and loue turnes her liking into loathing. Yea, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, vpon euery ſin, cut not the cord of vanitie, and grace grow vp in the roome with ſincerity, this death in ſinne, will bring death for ſinne, which will turne ſaluation offered, but careleſly reiected, into confuſion deſerued, but
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14143:53"/> now not greatly feared.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>LOue not (Reader) the works of darkneſſe, leſt thy eies cannot behold the light. To ſaue thee from ſinne, learne the commandements, know thy natural inclination, and ſtriue for amendment. Heare how God threats, and ſtand in awe; obſerue his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to diſcerne of his wrath. Other mens puniſhments for thy perſonall faults, make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admoniſhments that thou no more doe fall. Oppoſe Gods
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14143:53"/> precepts, to temptations of pleaſure, the reward of that heauenly life, to this temporv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and earthly loſſe. For ſake not God, for any worldly good. Sinne not heere, as a ſeruant to Satan: neglect not true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, which is with God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, and ſhall be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced with endleſſe happines. Remember thou muſt die, and therefore liue to die: Conſider the day of account to make a good reckoning. As thou art heere, ſo looke to ſtand there: if heere ſinnefull, there ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; if heere regardleſſe of the commandement, there cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:14143:54"/> expect ſeuere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; from which the Lord deliuer thee.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:14143:54"/>
            <head>The Picture of Heauen.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eauen is the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of reſt: deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all, hoped for of many; but onely enioyed of the beſt. It is the higheſt place, the ſeat and throne of God, the habitation of Angels, the harbour for the iuſt. It is the court of the great King, the mighty Creator.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14143:55"/> It is the Lords Tabernacle, the faithfull mans recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: the Region reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the comfortable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, the Citie of ſafetie, ſecurity: the ſacred ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie of peace, proſperitie. All in it are without miſery, neuer after ſubiect to cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie. It is a Paradiſe for pleaſure, a Citie for beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a Kingdome for ſtate. Heere is life tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, there life eternall: here the beginnings of grace, there the perfection of goodneſſe. There is God in his fulneſſe of glory, yet
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14143:55"/> to none dreadfull, there he raignes in iuſtice, and yet with none wrathfull. The company are all trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, as heere they haue beene members Militant. All is in tune, concord, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſcord; ſweet melody, neuer any bitter malady. Such fulneſſe there is of all things, ſuch loue mutually in all, ſuch reſpect from all to each others ſtate and place, as no exceſſe is ſeen, nor any defect is felt; who that haue leaſt can deſire no more, and thoſe that haue moſt, diſcerne no
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:14143:56"/> want in other. All is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe there without blemiſh, immeaſurable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all motion, excellent beyond all imagination. The wals thereof are of ſtones moſt precious, the ſtreets paued with pure gold, all the worke is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med curiouſly, ſet out with all ſorts of pearle very ſumptuouſly, and adorned with al skil moſtgloriouſly. It is decked with all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, repleniſhed with all pleaſure, garniſhed with algraces, beutified with the beſt companie, flouriſhing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14143:56"/> with the flowre of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. There is the roiall Prieſthood, the peculiar people, the children of light, the new creatures, the elect by Gods preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, the ſeparated So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety by Gods effectuall vocation, and the holy Saints by the ſpirits ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. There are metioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully together the Head and his body, Chriſt and his Church, the Prince of peace, with his Patriarks and Prophets, Prieſts and Profeſſors, Apoſtles and Apoſtolicall men, Saints,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14143:57"/> true ſeruants to God, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, and Martyrs for the truth. They are all there noble, none ignominious, all Kings raigning, all victoriouſly triumphing: None con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, all honourable. All inueſted in glory, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Maieſtie, cloathed in ſincerity. Their faces ſhine with comely beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, their hearts are filled with pietie, their tongues extoll the Lord with ſpirituall alacritie, and in their hands they hold Palms in token of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14143:57"/> This heauenly hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe cannot bee imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; the bleſſings are ſo many, they cannot bee numbred; ſo innumerable, as they cannot be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, ſo incomparable, as cannot be equaled; of ſuch value as cannot bee prized; ſo great, as not to bee meaſured; and of ſuch eternitie, as they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer can be ended. They be ioifull in an euer-reioicing ioy, they cry aloud Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah, and ſing cheerefully Halleluiah. They ſtand before the face of God in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14143:58"/> ineſtimable fauour, in the view of Angels with brightneſſe ouerſhining the Sunne. Mercy embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them, without doubt of miſerie: in comfort without diſcontentment, in peace endleſſe, in glory matchleſſe. There is mirth without ſadneſſe, health without ſickneſſe, ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of countenance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſorrow, tranquillity without vndermining tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie, liuelihood without labour, goods and riches without greeuance in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, without care in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping:
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14143:58"/> and a full felicity of all things without adding, without diminiſhing. Ther is flowriſhing youth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer decaying, ſtrength ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer abating, comelie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance neuer withering: liuelineſſe is without fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, couragiouſneſſe of heart and ſpirit without danting. There is euer loue without lothing or diſlike, victorie without feare of after vanquiſhment, glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without diminution of goodneſſe. Mortalitie hath put on immortalitie, corruption glorification.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14143:59"/> No ſin is there to be ſeene, the Law is fulfilled, the curſe is remoued, death ſubdued, the promiſes of the Goſpell fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. Faith hath her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect work in charitie, hope her deſired happineſſe, loue a large ſcope in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting vnitie. There is no Foe to fight, no Couſener to collogue, no Paraſite to diſſemble, no Superiour among them to command, no Inferiour to yeeld obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: no maligning enuie, no proud Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignetie. All are now
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14143:59"/> equall members, no diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded orders; no ſorrainers, but brethren; no ſtrangers, but all of the houſhold of faith: Children of one ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Father, coheirs with Chriſt, their elder brother. There are no teares, the cauſe is taken away: No torment, Chriſt freed them by his puniſhment; no dreade, Chriſt ſet them at libertie from death; no crying, there is no paine; no pangs or ſorrowfull paſſion, they poſſeſſe peace in Paradiſe. No diſeaſe can infect the body, it is
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14143:60"/> not ſubiect to ſickneſſe, it is freed from infirmities, and cannot be diſtreſſed by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities. There is no ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor ſobbing through ſorrow of heart, ſuch acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents cannot happen; no lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table complaints for iniuries offred, no wrongs can there be wrought. No ill ſucceſſe nor wofull wants, no griefe of mind nor anguiſh of ſpirit, no cruell oppreſſion, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous action find there a ſubiect to harbour in, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther practiſer nor patron. Care combers no mans
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14143:60"/> mind, nothing weakneth the vnderſtanding, nothing blunts the apprehenſion. Iudgement cannot bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with error, zeale with corrupt affection, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience with anger. Will is there without wilful fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, the heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deceit and hardneſſe. Thoughts are not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, they be not corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: affections not diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, they bee not diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. The holy ſpirit rules all, the holy Lamb leades all, God by his power pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues them, by his grace
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14143:61"/> doth euer aſſiſt them. All mercies are receiued thankefully, al commands are obeied rightly: in hart without hypocriſie, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie without grudging, readilie without lingring, faithfully without altering, ioifully without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and conſtantly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing. Their drinke is the ſweet water of life, Angels foode their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate nouriſhment, Chriſts righteouſneſſe their holie raiment, and their perfect fulnes ioifull contentment. In a word, there is happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14143:61"/> with goodneſſe, feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie with vnitie, ſafetie with ſolace, peace with perfection, pleaſure with profit, agreement with grace, lowlineſſe without contempt, exaltation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pride, ſecurity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out carnality, ſtability without wauering, abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance without euer-wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. All perſons general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie haue the participation of ioy, and euery one in particular the fruition of glory. Nothing there is here to the eie diſcernable, nothing there but innarra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14143:62"/> all things to humane reaſon incredible. A man may imagine much, a tong may ſpeake much, the eare may heare much, yet hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly happineſſe is beyond all relation, all imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The name of heauen to all is louely, many doe wiſh it hartily. All Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aime at it: the Iew ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects it, the Turke wiſheth it, the wickedeſt deſire it, the Papiſt would merit it, the Schiſmaticke ſeekes for it; the ſound Proteſtant, the deuout Chriſtian by faith begges it, and hee
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14143:62"/> through Ieſus Chriſt ſhall enioy it; to whom be praiſe and glorie for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>O Mortall man, doe thou often meditate of this happineſſe. Let it eat vp thy heart with deſire to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy it. Let carking for this world bee expelled with thy care of heauen: neglect not this felicity, the things heere are tranſitorie vanitie. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light not in the pleaſures of death, to loſe, for them, the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14143:63"/> paradiſe of life. To winne the world by works of darkneſſe, what is thy gaine, if thou loſe true goodneſſe? To pawne thy ſoule for ſinne, is it not mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Exchange not God for the Diuell, goodneſſe for bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, heauen for hell. Heauen is a holy place, the vncleane enter not thereinto. Suppoſe no ſuch eaſie paſſage, as fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Poets paint out: Straite is the way vnto it, narrow is the gate to goe into it: many ſeeke it, few doe find it. Let thy way be veritie; thy path pietie, the ſpirit thy condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, the word a directour, thy
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14143:63"/> eie faith, thy ſtaie hope. The ſtraitneſſe of it, is affliction; the narrowneſſe, true contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the ſuburbs, the Church; the dore, Chriſt: by whom thou ſhalt enter into the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, euen the Paradiſe of God. Striue then to auoid heere wickedneſſe, to eſcape all future wretchedneſſe, that thou maieſt poſſeſſe this true bleſſedneſſe for euermore. This God grant thee, Chriſt merit for thee, the holie Spirit therof certainely aſſure thee, and thy godlie life witneſſe the ſame to thee, that thou maieſt end thy daies comfortably.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="picture">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:14143:64"/>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:14143:64"/>
            <head>The Picture of Hell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ell is the place for the impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, euerie ſuch perſon is the helliſh inhabitant. It is the priſon for thoſe that be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the dreadful dungeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vtter darkenes, the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Topheth, and deep pit bottomleſſe. It is the lake
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14143:65"/> burning with brimſtone, the hollow caue and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os of confuſion. It is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour with lamentation, it is dread with deſolation, and horrour with vtter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. There is death, there is euer dying, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner without being. It is a gulph deuouring, a ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing whirle pole, a fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming furnace: Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice makes it, his power vpholds it, and it is blown with the bellowes of his wrath. There is ſcorching fire vnquenchable, and freezing cold intollerable.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14143:65"/> Stinking ſmoak is for the ſmell, loathſome filth for the ſtomacke: the eare ſhall heare a hideous noiſe, the eie ſhall ſee gaſtlie ſights, and horrible viſions: what not there to breed amazed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? what not there to cauſe fearefull aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? It is the valley of Gods vtmoſt vengeance, the fulneſſe of his wrath, &amp; perfection of his plagus. The Lords gaole, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilement of ſoules, the ſinck of ſinners, the foule har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for infernall Hags. Oh what woe is there with
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14143:66"/> wailing from hearts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe; what riuers of teares, becauſe of tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring torments, and yet remedileſſe? Forlorne creatures, curſed caitifs; full of trauell, painefull wearines: ful of frightings, fearefull terrours endleſſe. They bee in themſelues helpeleſſe, of Gods mercy hopeleſſe. Oh the clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous outcrying, the yelps and yelling, the ſighs and ſobbing, the mad rage that there is and roaring! No heart ſo hard, as can ſuffer a mortall eie to behold it,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14143:66"/> no eare to heare it, nor mind to muſe of it. The diuell there hath his full damnation, the fiends are outragious and filled with furie, the reſt fret and ſume, and are as in a wood fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. Their deſire is reuenge, their deuotion, curſing; their bleſſing, blaſpheming. The wicked there be ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goted vp with the bands of Gods iuſtice; as bundles of ſticks ſo caſt into the fire, by the power of his might, ſo held in vndura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torment by his perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſpleaſure, as they
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14143:67"/> blaſpheme Gods benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for feeling his iuſtice in ſeueritie. They bee in a huge Sea of miſerie, in an Ocean of calamitie. Fire, flames, and flaſhing about them, the worme of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience gnawing within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; rage, madneſſe, irefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: vgly viſages of blacke diuel saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighting them, monſtrous apparitions, an vncomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table companie about the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Sulphure and hot burning cinders vnder them: the reuenging hand of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, and pouring forth
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14143:67"/> the viols of his wrath, full of variety of plagues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing vpon them. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian plagues are there encreaſed, the tempeſts of lightening and thunder multiplied. They may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue from place to place, ſo exchange in plagues, but neuer either be eaſed of pangs, or freed from paine. They are chained vp perpetually, to endure reall puniſhment vpon body and ſoule eternally. They haue heauie hearts loadned with paſſion, they be wofully diſtreſſed with
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14143:68"/> all Calamities, without any commiſeration. There is care, but no comfort; vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, without conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; lamentation but none ſhew compaſſion. They weepe, they crie, they waile, &amp; mourne, they houle, and pitiouſly bemone their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-during miſerie. Ah, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, ſaith one, in cold free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and yet extremely burning: Woe to mee, ſaith an other, in hote wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ſcalding, and yet ſo cold, as his teeth may bee hard chattering, his body may behold ſo to quak, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14143:68"/> in euery ioint to quiuer, as if bone from bone would fall a ſunder. Hence ſuch roaring, ſuch yelling, ſuch bitterneſſe in banning, ſuch ſcritching and outcries, at the ſudden renewing of torments, at the continual remouing into exchange of tortures, and yet remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alwaies in contrarie plagues, as the eare neuer heard, the eie neuer ſaw nor minde of man able to apprehend: Wofull dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, horribly fearefull, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferably painefull. This ſtinking Sidde and dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14143:69"/> crawles full of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous generation, bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>Cainits,</hi> with ſorcerous <hi>Balaamites,</hi> perſecuting <hi>Saules,</hi> with craftie <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels,</hi> the Serpents ſeed, the reprobated race, and the accurſed workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. There the rageous may rend and teare one an other, and none part them; the enuious gnaſh for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and gnaw one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the bone, and none regard them. Hee that heere ſinned for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, will there ſinne more becauſe of his plagues.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14143:69"/> Euery ſinne ſhall there bee puniſhed, accordingly as they were here committed. There is penurie for glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie; extreame drineſſe and thirſting, for exeſſiue drinking; burning, for le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous luſting; outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous madneſſe, for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; want, for ill gotten wealth; a fearefull agonie, for bloody crueltie; for oppreſſion vtter deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Then is ſeene with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row enough their time ſpent in vanitie, their child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in fooliſhineſſe, their youth in luſtfulneſſe, their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14143:70"/> manhood in wickedneſſe, and their old age in coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, their firſt yeeres runne on in ignorance, the middle age conſumed in negligence, and the terme of life ended without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. They out of meaſure are vexed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what they were, and might haue beene, what they are, and muſt be, what they would be, and cannot attaine to. They thinke of time paſt, but without thought of recouery, they taſte of the time preſent in vnſpeakeable miſerie, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14143:70"/> doe looke to the time to come, without hope of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie. One curſeth his birth, and bewailes his ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; an other curſeth his education, and parents negligence; a third, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully bannes himſelfe for his irrepentance. Their owne ſenſes doe enlarge much their ſorrowes; they behold Heauen, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in Hell; the godly in gladneſſe, themſelues in griefe; Chriſts faithfull people in order, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, themſelues in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and fearefull horrour;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14143:71"/> the Saints of God in glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous proſperitie, themſelues in ſhamefull infamie, and miſerable aduerſitie. They heare in heauen bleſſing, melodious ſinging; in hell curſing and lamentable mourning; before the eies are flaſhing flames, and a thicke ſmoake aſcending; for the noſe is prepared a noiſome ſmell euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſtincking. In ſteed of ſweetneſſe, there is gallie bitterneſſe; for delicate fare, farniſhment; for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, inthralement; fire brands, for beds; for ſoft
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14143:71"/> lodging, pich and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone with iuniper coales burning; in ſteed of muſick and pleaſant harmonie, a helliſh noiſe of diſcordan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. They feele torments vnſpeakable, paines intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, and the ſame al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies durable. By impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence their plagues are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, by their obſtinacy continued, and by Gods power and iuſtice maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Thus are their hearts in continuall heauineſſe, their pale countenance in dolefull ſadneſſe. To heauen they looke vp, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14143:72"/> their miſhap, in hel they looke downe with ſhame of face. If they would repent now they cannot: if they could, it is then to late; they were retchleſſe in the daies of amendment, and their caſe is remedileſſe, in the time of puniſhment. There is not any grant of the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the greateſt tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor to the extreemeſt pange any kind of eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They may crie, and cry againe, Lord, Lord; they may intreat for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but neuer be heard: no
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14143:72"/> grace, no peace, all paine, all plagues; none bleſſed, euery one accurſed. Hee that is afflicted, ſhall bee more tormented; he that is condemned, ſhall euer be damned. Heauen haue they loſt, and not to bee purchaſed, Hell haue they duelie deſerued, and the place muſt needes bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured. None among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues can helpe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and among the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall companie they ſhall not finde one comforter. If children ſhould call to parents, they will not pity
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:14143:73"/> them they haue loſt that naturall affection, they can haue no ſuch compaſſion. Though parents ſhould make petition &amp; pray their children, they will not bee cared for. Tho they cry and call, ſaying ôh our bowels, and our blood. Oh once bone of our bone, and fleſh of our fleſh, ſpeake for your poore tormented pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: Is there no naturall loue now left? What no compaſſion? Shall wee periſh? can you ſee vs thus plagued, and ſhew no pitie? Haue mercy,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14143:73"/> deare children, on vs ſo in miſerie, ſweet Babs, once louing and beloued, ſpeak, oh ſpeake one word for vs; are wee not plunged in vnſpeakable paine? looke vpon your now forlorne Father, who once fedde you with food: ah, alas, haue ſome remorſe of your mournefull mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Oh for Gods ſake ſeeke this time our good: let ſome ſparkles of your loue appeare. Can you be in pleaſure, and ſuffer vs to lie in perpetuall paine? Wee ſpared no labour
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14143:74"/> for your education, and can your eies behold vs languiſhing in this place of deſtruction? If you did call, wee came ſpeedily to ſuccour: when we heard you cry, wee were in care for you; your miſerie was to vs calamitie; your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, the abatement of our proſperitie; and can you heare our pitious gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſee the Diuels grinning as dogs vpon vs, your eares heare our bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter crying and they againe barbarouſly tormenting vs and be ſilent? Oh, woe is
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14143:74"/> vnto vs, fire, conſume vs; vengeance, doe you vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie make an end of vs. All this will not worke, words are but ſpent in vaine; na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures force hath loſt the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect; there is no knowledge of kindred, or kinsfolke; the godly regard Gods glorie, and therein onely reioice. To conclude, they now know, and to late be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that the good doe dwell with God, haue Chriſts company and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels glorie; but themſelues to be hated of God, negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of the good: to bee
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14143:75"/> with black diuels damned, with ſauage furies accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied, with barking hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hounds horribly affrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and with barbarous tormentors cruelly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; ſo as they alwaies in this liueleſſe liuing, weepe, mourne, and lament for ſuch helliſh paines: and in this deathleſſe dying crie, yelp, howle, yell, for ſuch euer during plagues: from which (O Lord) deliuer thine, and ſhew them mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie (O God) that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay not in goodnes, that ſo they neuer feele theſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14143:75"/> for their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Amen.</p>
            <div type="precepts">
               <head>Precepts.</head>
               <p>O Miſerable Sinner, now doe thou ſeriouſlie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider: heere in this life, ſee to thy ſelfe. Who would endure, but awhile theſe paines, for all worldly pleaſure? Who would goe to this dolefull place of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, for wicked gaine? What is there in this pleaſure heere, profit, and honour, that for it thou ſhouldſt aduenture infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall paines for euer? Oh breake the caul of thine heart with
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14143:76"/> ſorrow, rather then to fall into ſuch plagues, for delight in ſinne. Bruſt into teares, to eſcape theſe torments. Liue not ſecurelie; ſtoope hautie heart, that thou maieſt not for pride bee ſent packing to this place of paines. Grow leane cheekt thou Glutton, and pale faced thou Drunkard, ere thou beeſt euerlaſtinglie fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with penurie, or be ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in a burning flame, and euer be kept drie and thirſtie. Thou mincing creature Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock-like, neglect thy pride i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> apparell, that thou maieſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in time auoid this perill.
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14143:76"/> Prophane Miſcreant, ſeeke an attonement, labour for peace, fall downe before the throne of grace. Let (O wicked liuer) thy head be a fountaine of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cauſe thy eies to tric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle downe teares, yea to runne as riuers for thy tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that thou maieſt eſcape theſe helliſh vexations. Looke on the ground whereon thou goeſt, and thinke vpon thy graue: behold the heauens, and conſider whence is grace. Aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie regard the accuſation of conſcience, and ſet euer thy ſelfe before Gods preſence. Read letters of diſcomfort
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14143:77"/> ſometime from the Law, leſt thou preſume by promiſes of the Gospell. Draw neere to God, whileſt he doth ſay, Come; ſtretching out his hands to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the penitent: before he ſaie, Goe, ſitting as Iudge to condemne the diſobedient. There is a time for thee before thou die to obtaine ſaluation; but in time after death there is no redemption. Therfore craue pardon of God earneſtly, aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate thy ſelf to the godlie ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie. Fall groueling vpon the ground, and aske forgiueneſſe: grieue heartily, ſpeake paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately. Smite thy breaſt, ſtrike
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14143:77"/> on thy thigh, ſhake thy head, wring thy hands, ſhead teares, powre, powre out thy ſoul vnto God, and crie aloud, aloud, I ſaie, cry, oh ſpare ſpare me good Lord, whom thou (O God) haſt redeemed with Chriſts precious blood. Oh forgiue me, I confeſſe I haue offended thee: let thy patience forbeare mee, let thy great mercie acquite mee. He that doth repent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, the Lord will heare him in time: Gods gracious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, is neuer without piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full commiſeration: neither the prouoking of his iuſtice to wrath, without dreadfull and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14143:78"/> certaine deſtruction. Preſume not, yet despaire not; liue to die, yet die to liue; thinke of heauen, yet forget not, that there is a hell: be ſo comforted in thy iuſtification, as thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer get a certaintie of glorie by thy ſanctification. Liue in the fleſhes mortification, in hatred of the world, in the ſpirits viuification; vſe the meanes of thy effectuall voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: claime nought of merit, craue all of mercie, liue in true humilitie, and practiſe alway the works of charitie, and thou ſhalt aſſuredly eſcape Hels</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14143:78"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
